[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
welcome everyone this is the stoa
the the store is a place to dialogue
around what matters most at the nice
edge
of history and
um we're going to try to
uh hone that knife's edge a little today
so
here we are uh this is a series an
offering called high pitch conversations
in a new key
and i just wanted to uh sh
to give credit to a philosopher
philosopher called
susan langer she wrote a book called
philosophy in a new key so that really
actually
does one of the reasons why we have this
it resonates off of that
you're going to meet us all in this
conversation
um myself bonnie and ria and nora
and skye and miriam and eche
very brief history this is
emerged from um conversations i had
starting a couple of years ago
where people after doing a podcast would
say
why aren't there not more women in this
space who do you recommend
and what would happen at that time is
i would immediately many women's names
would come to my
uh in my imagination but i'm like really
they're not gonna
they're not gonna do a rebel wisdom
podcast there was like a disconnect
between
the framing that the podcast offers in
what these women could offer
so is there a disconnect between the
constraints of the medium
and the real juice and gem
of the way i was talking to some
to some of these women so we started
looking at this
consciously starting with a
and and skye and i and
yeah and it took a while for us to
allow more
information to come in and
show us what this might be and then we
had a little bit of
email conversation amongst all of us
and what we decided together
to seed this first conversation
is a little bit of a dialogue around
uh conversation
what for us personally do we find
missing
from this ecology of podcasts
that um that connect us
what kind of conversation are we
starving to see reflected back to us
right this is a very powerful you know
when you grew up in the 60s and you saw
tv and you saw like families acting a
certain way
you were ashamed because your family
didn't act like that
didn't give you permission to be who you
were and something like that happens
sometimes in the podcast space you're
like well
i don't reason like that i don't talk
like that
and so there's a there's a phenomenon
that is like a is like shame like and so
uh part of what we're hoping to do is
bring
into the light this whole other vast
resource of conversation
and knowledge um
that we think people are starving for uh
in the public realm
and that we can build capacity through
that feedback loop
so um yeah what how would you how would
you describe
what's missing in the space what what
what would
you love to see tune in and see
um conversation um
yeah and then we can just talk about
some of the ways we
name this later if we want to do that
but
um yeah what do you see is
the conversation that has most air time
uh what kind of conversations would do
you think
would be valuable to see reflected in
the public space
are you opening it up oh no this first
is for our panel discussion
thanks for asking um
i can jump in hi bonnie hi everyone
so uh as you asked that question the
first thing that comes to my
mind and my heart is what i would love
to see more of and hope maybe we can
bring is
a movement from the theoretical to the
embodied to the practical to the daily
life
so while i love the cognitive
explorations
and sort of the intellectual gymnastics
that can happen
and the deeper depths and the
widths and the breadths of sense-making
that can happen in that
theoretical space i think um
what feels very pressing to me both
individually and as i look out and and
feel the world is how can we actually
bring these insights that we have right
into cut really into our daily bread
like how we show up with our kids how we
show up with our partners
um how we spend our days uh so that
that's sort of one
little beginning impulse that is present
i i just really want to second that
miriam and
say that i i
i find so often that um
you know benito was talking about shame
and that there's um
a very real experience of
of having this toggle of
if either you're speaking in the
cognitive
theoretical space and so you're showing
that you know your theory
okay and that gives you some sort of
expertise or credibility
for being in the complexity realm
but um the other thing
is to be talking about how
that embodied understanding of the
theory
is played out in daily life
and very often people don't recognize it
when it's in daily life because it's not
labeled
it's not inside the jargon you don't
talk about your kids
you know decoupling or you know having
these sort of
various complexity terminology
uh applied to them and yet
my dad used to always say it doesn't
count till you have it in your elbows
right and so for me this this is this
has been a source
of just
so much um misunderstanding
of of times when i have tried to really
show up
in my most human self
and getting dismissed for it people not
actually being able to perceive the
theoretical work that i
am i am bringing through that process
without the labels it doesn't get
noticed
so yeah thank you
i want to jump in and add how i
throughout the years that i've been
studying this stuff
um how i've been
getting in the business of all the
mentors and teachers i've been working
with just
pushing them to reveal what time do you
wake up
what's the first thing you do how do you
deal with this how do you deal with that
like just wanting to understand
you know how if this
can produce a lot of writing how is it
that
at what time and you know for how long
do you write is that level of
personal revealing that i would love to
see more of
from all these people i look after you
know
it's a just a real quick one because i'd
like everyone obviously to speak um
but i just thought it was interesting um
how you said how you look up to them
and then i was thinking what is the lens
that i hold as i'm
regarding these people on podcasts and i
realize the lens i hold
is actually how well do they embody this
stuff
like i will take someone way more
seriously
if they are living and breathing what
they're talking about so i just thought
i'd add that little note
and to pick up from there um
in our email exchange we had
over the last weeks
i also put up the ques the question like
can we actually
be it right here right now
together can we embody
in the conversation
can we actually show
how complexity sits in a good
conversation and in a dialogue
and
i've been searching the web
to actually find it but
it hardly was it hardly is there and
um
i go with your lens miriam like
are they embodying it or is it
theory or
and it made me aware of
how
that the mental
few on things or the intellectual
is still
at least in in this kind of medium is is
still
um more valued or higher valued or
as much as as
we think that things are more balanced
but
around knowing or
i don't know how else to call it
there's a lot that we could and
should and need to explore i think
yeah that's me for now
i'll jump in uh ria i just noticed how
calm
i feel when you speak
um which is nice because what i was
gonna add is that
um i often feel like i have like a wild
animal
inside of me when i'm in these spit when
not this space checking it yeah it's
still there the wild animal
and it's like you know we've tamed
conversations so much
and there's some deeper
um experience that i'm yearning
for like when you said what are you
hungry for what are you starving for
i'm really hungry for experiences where
i can um
be a little bit wilder
like a little more unpredictable
and and that maybe others would feel
comfortable to be
a little more unpredictable like bonnie
you always talk about
your job being to insert novelty into
the conversation and
i love that because it just brings for
me it brings things
to life and um
yeah and there's some aspect for me too
and i don't know if this is personal but
i
i'm sure others there are others for
whom this will resonate
the emotional experience
like my my tuning fork like the way i
move through the world is
very for better or worse
emotionally tuned and so
um yeah sometimes i find that there's
not really
and it could be me projecting this but i
i do find that there's maybe not
as much space for me to express emotions
um and part of that is that i'm afraid
that if i express
them they will be misunderstood or you
know they won't
there won't be space for them somehow so
it's me with my you know it's kind of
like me
fighting my own taming the wild animal
and the tame part
yeah thank you
yeah so this is interesting already
because
you know in these there part of this is
this notion of
forwarding this into the public realm
and there's only so many
models and of course uh
there's a strange attractor how do we
perform what is
what is the implicit rules and the
models
like this is stereotypical and it's just
to frame the conversation but in general
the models are like
women show up as uh like
performance like the view like there's a
lot of performance happening and there's
a lot of emotional
kind of things happening in
those spaces so you can have a lot of
emotion
but then in these spaces these new kind
of
series and podcasts and this in this
ecology
and ignoring this is you'll know this
it's like the price of admission to
express an emotion
is to show you're very very cognitively
complex
and that's what doesn't bring people
like skyler and echa in
that's the price of admission if you can
prove yeah i understand yeah i
understand yeah i understand yeah i
understand
that but then i'm saying this is very
simple
then you're trustworthy and that's the
price of admission
to express an emotion in these spaces
and it's not about only emotions
but it's also what i call that inner
knowing
that intuition the uh
the sense you have of something it's not
even
real emotion like sadness or happy or
anger or frustration but there's so much
more
formats or i don't find the right word
of knowing that they're also
important and that we need to balance
and that will actually
actually we need that wholeness i call
it the wholeness of knowing for actually
sensing and knowing what is
the next step we can take um
yeah it's it's like there's these
scripts
and um there are different scripts for
different
sorts of zones um you know there's kind
of a
this sort of script and that sort of
script and
and um
then there's how you're living your life
and the way that you approach
breakfast the way that you are
in interaction with your family
the way that you're in interaction with
your own body
your own transformations in this time
because
that is what's happening um is
is requiring
a completely different tonality and
texture
of of exploration okay and so that
exploration is going to have a different
kind of expression
and and so we don't there's just not a
space
to have that kind of expression of
of um
this sense of
careful wordless
fumbling um
sometimes it's poetic right it's the
difference between
talking about whatever the
the complexity is and being within it
and that transmitting that sensibility
of being within
[Music]
the the complexity of of all that we
you know we and there's everyone sort of
in a lot of transformations right now uh
what what is it what does it feel like
where where is it and
if you also have kind of the
the theoretical work in there the way
that
that is able to be held is really
different
right so the the the way that my
irritation say with my 15 year old
stepson comes into
communication and conversation is
coming through a lifetime of working
with systems and complexity and there's
all of these things are there
and they are they're they're they're
informing and they're
they're helping me to to find a way to
deal with difficult moments
that are not moments to turn to the
blackboard and start talking about
complexity their moments to be in life
but to be in the complexity and not
screw up the relational processes and
that's what this is all about
is being in the deep
sometimes no worded emotional
relational um processes and they have
they they go
out right you know then you can they
they go into more relationships and more
relationships and
if we're talking complexity theory we
start talking about second and third
order processes
but what we're really talking about is
how my kid then goes to school and feels
in his classroom
for the rest of the day and
and you know tending to that that
multiple layered relational process is
what we are doing
right those are the pathways that go
to the future
i love that i just wanted to notice
maybe others are noticing it too just a
different pace that we're having which
i'm really enjoying um
there's a couple things that feel alive
one is that this conversation feels like
it has spaciousness
um i'm not feeling sometimes i'm in
these kind of conversations and it's
like
there's actually something that would
like to be spoken through me or someone
else and you can hardly get a word in
so even the fact that when one of us has
spoken there's a little space
feels like already part of that movement
that we're talking about
of embodying um and the other
thing i wanted to share was as you were
speaking nora
i could feel i'm curious how this lands
for you but i could feel how
when we are bringing the the muchness
the complexity into daily life in my
experience there's actually a
there's a thread through that is
actually very simple
because it it would be quite impossible
to bring all the different angles and
perspectives and systems upon systems
and
the whole thing can feel like a big
carriage how are you ever going to fit
that
into how are you going to chat with your
15 year old
but when you start embodying simply the
the growing
circles of care concern compassion
the living into the great mystery and
the breadth and width and depth that we
can all
you know fill um when that starts
happening
in your actual being then in in my
experience
there is a simplicity i'm not bringing
it all i'm actually just showing up with
a trust that it is there and uh
and in a way a stepping into the unknown
and not having to show up as the one who
knows
but i think that maybe is also something
that i
would yearn for in these podcast spaces
is that
we don't all have to show up as experts
we can actually
know what we know and share it which is
awesome but also
really be there present with the edges
that we don't have a clue about
or that we're just very curious about
and inquisitive and
looking to find out together
i would like to highlight what i just
heard that's most important
for me um
you know i have a five-year-old child
and
most of my time is still very much being
a mother
like 90 95 of my time it feels like
and um um
miriam is you said something about the
being of it
uh the moment of uh
of that practice when as mothers were
trying to embody um certain ways of
being
is actually simple uh
it is that simplicity that i would love
to hear us and other people
to to start trying to express
like
and i know bonnie hates it hates it when
i say principles and guiding principles
but i have that kind of tendency to
look for um north
stars at least if not
mean i do not believe in set in
principle set in stone principles but
um i feel like there are certain north
stars that
could guide us in settling into that
simplicity
of just being with the understanding
that it is our
being that is wiring
the child in front of us
um and that wiring is what is going to
carry that
this new newly forming human
uh for the rest of his life so
it it matters greatly
how he gets wired in the early years of
his life
it's just so interesting because there's
so much of the communication that just
has to do with not
diving into the cultural script that has
been written for us and uh
that is sometimes the hardest thing in
the world to do
whether it's to not say the thing or to
respond in a way that's off off off
off the teleprompter and it's i mean the
the
the compelling urge to say the thing
um i remember this one time when my
daughter
was i don't know she was like 14 15. i
walked into her room and it was a
complete mess
right clothes all over the floor my
clothes
and um and that she had borrowed i
walked in and
it's it happened here it comes my god
how do you even think in here this place
is a disaster
i spend all this money on things for you
and this is how you
you know can you hear the script do you
know the script we know the script
and she looked at me and she was like
she looks a lot like me and she had this
like red hair and she was fire
and she said you can't tell me how to
live my life
okay and in that moment on the
teleprompter there's a few options
right and one of them is young lady
don't talk to me like that
another one sounds like well as long as
you live under my roof i sure do have
the right to
right okay we know these things
and somehow like you were saying miriam
in that moment i
what i saw was this
fire and i thought my god this is so
beautiful this fire what
damage it would be to
break this fire i don't even want to say
dampen it but to break the fire
and i just looked at her and i was like
you're right i don't have the right to
tell you what to do and she just knew i
was going to come back with one of those
script lines she was ready she was
and then it wasn't there
and what happened in that moment was
not only did we have a shifting of
arrangement about what was important in
life which is
fairly significant but we also had a
moment
around what it feels like to get off the
cultural scripts
together and and she got to see me
learning something and changing my path
sensing something i didn't know i was
gonna
sense responding differently and
actually altering the course of the
relational process
and you know that's i think that's what
we're talking about
is it's in those moments and it's in
your those moments with your partners
too
like that that thing of just you know
when you're really looking at this
incredible complexity of life like
seriously
what do you want someone to promise you
that's a whole different kind of
question
how do you want to be how do you want to
be in relationship
with someone given the complexity of at
all
what is that and that's a different kind
of question so
i think this is an important shift
because
that's the disservice that a lot of
these complexity i mean there's a time
for the theory
and there's a time to look at complex
systems from a theoretical
point of view
like hydrology and plasma movements and
stuff like that but there's a real
question whether
systems models are appropriate to human
experience
so probably an unexamined assumption
and the real disservice is that it takes
people away
from where they can actually enter
this beautiful complexity
because because the the entry point is
every place in your life because your
life is complex
nature's complex and so
on a piggyback off this uh story
there's a million stories you don't mean
or i know we have a million stories but
this one came up
so by default i get it from my mom
you know i really like to cook and i
have a big kitchen and i really like it
clean
you know when you like to clean and my
partner
of 30 years
he likes to use the computer on the
kitchen table and he does his
you know he uses he loves to be in the
kitchen he doesn't like to work in an
office and he is like he grew up
italian family everything's done in the
kitchen
and so his books and his
magazines and his unpaid bills and his
computers and his
his keys and his coach they're all over
the kit
it's a it's it's like so i watch this
torture me
right and i notice i just notice
and i and i turn it from like i'm angry
at him
to like what's that in me right
and i watch it over and over again and
then one christmas he got a chainsaw
for christmas and he put the chainsaw
on my dining room table
and i watched that work on me right that
it was there for like
five months now the thing is it's not
like he sees it and he's like i'm
getting at her
he doesn't see it it's just a chainsaw
on a dining room table
right and the truth is all of these
things that drive us crazy
are just like that they're just silly
concrete things
that are scripted in us in these
pathological ways
so i watched that i was teaching my
course and i go in and tell the
students every month you know i'm still
watching that thing
and it resolved itself by itself
but it never fully resolved in me right
quiet now that sounds silly
it's nice sorry about the dog but i'll
just leave it at that
like these opportunities
yeah this is where the opportunities are
yeah i'm just noticing in both your
stories the inner
competence you know the the inner
awareness
that nora you had in that moment that
you were able to see what was happening
in you
and see your daughter
and i love how you described her i could
see her too as you described her
um and bonnie you too i mean you're
always a model
for me of this kind of process of like
really i watched
how it was working on me you know
um yeah and i still
i mean
i i would spend a lot of time working on
my inner
competence as a
mystic and tantric practitioner like a
lot of my practice
is is the inner awareness
and still when the rubber hits the road
when it comes to
parenting i mean this could this could
potentially just be a conversation about
parenting um or relationships or
whatever else
um it's all right there right but it is
for me the parenting that
really is the big uh test
of all my so-called
spirituality um and it's such a gift
it's such a gift i have fortunately a
very
no-nonsense nine-year-old girl
and she won't take it she points out the
inconsistencies
all the time and she because of the
pandemic i'm doing a lot of my work in
front of her
which is kind of amazing because i'm
doing a lot of coaching
and very deep one-on-one work with
people and you know i'm mostly wearing
headphones so that
and and she's not always around but um
but sometimes she's hearing me you know
in a conversation like this or
coaching someone or talking someone
through something and then i turn around
and yell at her for whatever it is and
she's just like
okay i don't know maybe you need a coach
um and it's hard but it's lovely and
it's
and i'm thinking you know it's like the
children and then
i often find you know also the the gift
of
friends i have who are at another life
stage you know like maybe elderly
um i spent a lot of time with my
grandparents even into my 40s
they were kentucky farmers and it was
such a gift
to go every once in a while leave new
york city and
spend 24 or 48 hours in their household
and just i mean just
land completely in their presence and
it was that was a profound experience i
keep they keep coming back into my
consciousness as we talk about this too
and i want to pick it up um
also to to stand up against
how others see you parenting yeah
one thing is in your own house or
i remember being in a family
reunion whatever it was and my dad's son
probably six or seven doing something
nasty i don't remember what
but i kind of hit him i mean
not very hard but that was the pattern
you know like
nora was dying and then
yeah first of all he wasn't used to that
i would do that
so he immediately he kicked me back yeah
which is
a normal healthy response so and i
i stopped and i didn't say anything and
i remember my mother-in-law kind of
trying to force me to to say something
to him because that was not appropriate
but i was like
this is healthy if you get kicked you
kick
back kind of and
the the point was more to stand up
against
her view of me being the mother
with my then alice so
that and yeah there's so
many
examples of
yeah can we
yet to to actually choose
to step out of that mold and
again and again and again um
and probably help each other to step out
of the mold
and
and not give up i mean the
the conditioning is so deep and so
old and
yeah that was my contribution for now
um i'd like to
bring in the future here as i've been
listening i'm hearing how we are all
working with patterning that comes from
our past
and um there was something you said
nora about it we were talking about how
can you bring that complexity into life
and then there's a simplicity
and it can be hard right because you're
sort of going right on the edge
and you don't really have scripts that
you can follow
so that that was sort of the the feeling
there a future um
how can we you know one one of the
questions i hold a lot in my work with
parents is how can we
recreate culture in our families how can
we do it in our partnerships
and and how do we do it partly for me
it's
yes becoming very aware of the scripts
that come from the past and know how to
navigate them and become much more
competent with that navigation
the other piece is to to use the
yearning we have towards the future to
use our imagination that we have
of a possible future and even to use
literally any any way we can inhabit
a possible future that feels more sane
that feels more whole like can we
actually inhabit that even if just for
momentary states
to then inform us back to the present
moment
um and i was chuckling as sky you were
talking about your daughter
listening to you coaching in a way i
hear the dynamic right there i mean
i teach a course for years now called
parenting as a spiritual practice so i
had a five-year-old who would look at me
once in a while put her
put her hands on her hips and say mama
that's not parenting it's a spiritual
practice
and literally the only thing i could do
in that moment was like yeah you're
right
you know and part of the context
within which i was teaching and which
we've been parenting her
is it's a journey we just doesn't mean
we have to be there to be able to embody
the culture
we are talking about so we can actually
be very inspired we can speak about it
we can coach others in it and
we're making our way there we'll fall
flat on our faces at times
and so then we can actually model i
think for our kids also
saying sorry or i really didn't get that
one right
um which i also heard in in the weave of
your sharings
it's funny because it seems like there's
um first of all i i just have to say
that i completely agree with you and in
in the discussion of you know what what
kind of change
what what is the future all of this for
me that
lies absolutely in the intergenerational
relationships
um and and what is so tricky is that
in some frameworks of the way
we are often in pods talking about the
theoretical and cognitive aspects of
complexity
this piece um defies
any kind of logic that could be
[Music]
theorized upon that you could that you
could map
there is the deep experience of identity
and and how that is i mean
why do we do the things we do we you
know there's so many things that we do
that don't make any sense but we do
them because because why and
and somewhere in there is for me this
it's really relevant that we are talking
about family
and the way that family is at the core
of systems change and and it's not even
i mean
some of the family members you may not
be in communication with you may they
may be dead and gone
you know generations ago but they're
still
moving through us and
the ways in which i might respond in a
moment
how much of that is me
and how much of that is actually
something that that came before and and
sort of that
that attention like so that's what
happened in that moment with my daughter
was there was attention
to what i saw in her fiery self
was actually that
if i laid that down in that moment
i was gonna set something
and that thing that was going to get set
was going to actually be
a pivot in what it was possible to
communicate
for i don't know how many years in the
future so it wasn't what was
communicated
that was communicated it was what was
possible
to communicate that was communicated if
that makes any sense
so it wasn't it wasn't that i just
didn't say the thing it's that
between the two of us we had a moment
where we went somewhere else entirely
and that meant that from then on that
door was open
right and that is a shifting a whole
shifting of
of you know of of the possible
and and that happens in in one second
if you i had one second to see that
so how many generations did it take
to prepare for that one minute when i
could be
there and how to share that
right so that we don't have to wait
several generations
because it's it's there it's always
there
it's just that sometimes you can't see
it
or the patterns run so deep they just
they're driving you itself
to get off of them yeah
i'd like to break in here and ask each
one of you who have
children i don't have children
um a simple reflective question
and i kind of want to start with eche
because i know this is kind of
in your in your field of vision
if you could reflect on this question
when you look at your child
what what is the future you see in them
maybe just we can end with your
reflections on that what is when you
what is the future you see in your
children
that wasn't doesn't come from your past
thank you for asking that
yeah that that has been a north star
kind of orientation i feel
since i've become a mom um
i've been obsessed with this question of
how how do we raise
the new human you know because i
witnessed this
new consciousness come and come on to
earth into his
body i've been um
facilitating that helping him out in
this process
um so it is constantly that i
hold this question how do i not
bog him down uh with the cultural
social and the personal limitations that
i
carry
so that he can fulfill
so that he can fully potentiate
uh to exist to function
and hopefully even flourish in a very
troubling
world that he's inheriting at the moment
um you know from the
world side that is inheriting i have no
idea what's coming
i just have a sense that it's not going
to be easy at
all so then
i take my job really seriously as to
how do i um at all
planes of existence at the concrete
level like the
bodily you know nervous system level
um at the emotional regulation and you
know thinking
processed level and at the spiritual
level
um how do i set a foundation that allows
for
a human who can flourish
regardless of of the environment
or he knows how to make the choices
that will allow him
and you know and
the environment that he's going to be
um which is planet earth you know
um like how does he then also become
an agent of uh movement in the right
direction
because we need to be doing a lot of
that
um
yeah i'll just leave it at that for now
i can pick it up um i have three sons
and i have
seven grandchildren and
i can see in the grandchildren who are
between
between two and eleven at the moment
and how they have
almost all of their energy does
go into exploration
and learning and figuring things out
and it's
amazing to see just from
let's say my generation to them
at least for my family how
less they are burdened by by the past
like they're just there's so much
freedom
that they
they don't have many of these
scripts that were used at least when i
was young
kind of uh imprinted like every day
for years on end and they have way more
freedom
and way more parents like
h.a and skye and miriam
and so i see there
a lot more potential that can actually
be developed
and is developing from when they're
just a couple of months old and it's
in the beginning i was surprised and it
was i thought it was exceptional but
now that the high of seven it seemed
like whoa
yeah so in that way it's kind of
also hopeful at least for
the kids who can grow up in that way i'm
not saying it's happening everywhere
but that's what i see from my
perspective
i have six kids in my life um two
are from my body and four are my
from my husband's previous
marriages and um
i have been i was raised by somebody who
actually was aware of the
interdependencies and systems and all
this stuff that we're talking about so
i had a model um i had it i
had um i didn't know what that was
but you don't have to know because what
happens with parenting what happens
across generations
is not explicit it's it's in the
it's an indirect communication that this
that this really gets transmitted
um and my kids i was careful
and i paid attention and i was on it and
i knew they're coming into a world
that's changing
and i did all sorts of things i could
tell you hours of stories about them
um but but i can tell you one thing that
i didn't do
which was that in all of my workings
with them
in all kinds of ways
i didn't really take into account
not only their ability to be in the
world that was changing
but that they were going to be in really
close relationships
with other people who didn't know how to
do that
okay this was a piece that i missed
and um and it was it was you know
of course i was always you know modeling
that that
thing of being in relationship and
having communication
but what happens when you're in
relationship with people who have no
idea how to have those
kinds of communication and and so
um they have been through the dark night
i mean the generation of the
20-somethings ha
and they were in in university in the us
and they had partners that were dealing
with addiction
um suicide and you know we have been
through it and in those moments you
better
be able to be there and and so for me
this
is the real crunch right like
it's it's in those moments when you
really need
to be able to
perceive without a lot of wishy-washy
jargon what it is to be in the
interdependency of life
it's got to be on board it's not a it's
not a practice that's out here somewhere
it's
it's it's here um we were speaking
earlier about this
notion about being an expert
and this is something that i have pushed
hard on
with my with my in my whole life because
i was that little kid too
this idea that only adults of a certain
kind of
educational level can comprehend
complexity i'm calling
full tilt on that full tilt
my kids all got it all the people that i
work
with around the world that have you know
no education whatsoever
they get it and part of it has to do
with
this thing of going through the dark
night of meeting
real difficulty in life and recognizing
that it isn't single cause that the
causation
is multiple that there are all sorts of
processes that are all around it and
that's it i mean that's the stuff right
there
so this to me seems like the thing
and we're looking at the next generation
and what do we see
they're gonna be going along a road
that's going to ask them to actually
um be in a kind of grace
with extreme difficulties
it already is and they're multiple
layers and they're coming
more than one at a time and so
that i mean ultimately it requires a lot
of love and a sense of humor
and a a you know a keen intellect
and a lot of compassion and empathy and
art
so that's that's kind of what i'm
working with
i'd like to jump in because um at the
beginning of the pandemic
nora offered a beautiful weekly call for
parents
about schooling last spring when none of
us knew what we were doing
and i've learned so much from her in
this regard and that was
that was beautiful um so
yeah i mean the one thing i'll add and
um
is that and i don't know if this is good
advice or bad advice but
we have a saying my daughter and i
that there are rules there are capital r
rules and there are
small r rules and she's been brought up
mostly in brooklyn in new york city
and i'm often
pointing out to her like she has a very
different relationship to authority i
guess is where i'm
kind of going with this um in part
because she's watching
the political shenanigans as a
nine-year-old it's incredible like she
sees
right through um and
and we talk a lot in the city about and
with school
as she goes to a public school
and there have been times when i've
really that's really been hard for me
and then there have been times when it's
been an incredible opportunity to teach
her a lot
about which rules she needs to follow
and which rules
we don't necessarily need to follow and
i model that a lot um
uh yeah yeah i think i think that's it i
just
you know her relationship to authority
is very very
very different and her inner authority
is really what i'm trying to
nurture in her because i foresee also
that it's going to be an incredibly
um i don't even know what the word is
challenging probably doesn't capture it
but
at the at the end of the day i want her
to be
because she came in this way anyway like
very strongly in her center
and very perceptive and i like a little
no-nonsense
and i see that in a lot of children
actually they're
very aware of the climate situation we
haven't really
mentioned that overtly but they feel it
they already have a sense um for what
they're gonna be
dealing with she's been to so many
marches she has a favorite march
um so you know she's like
really engaged and really navigating by
her own inner authority
and that's what i try to nurture
i do we still have time yeah
so um just first i love your question
i've been bathing in it since you asked
it bonita
um i've been kind of looking in my
daughter's eye she's 17 now and just
with that question not actually she's at
school right now but like
in in my imagination i've been looking
in her eyes and just looking at the
future that i see in there
um so there's a few things
because she's 17 wow nora when you spoke
it like it was such a
my whole body was just feeling the
for me the uh i find it intense to be
parenting now
and knowing that the future is this
unknown i it breaks it literally breaks
my heart
in a very visceral way and and we have
since she was born been working so hard
to recreate culture in our family and
in our greater family and community and
environment
um but god it it's slow
you know it's it's slow so there's a lot
of heartache there
um there's there's actually i have fear
too um but when i look into her
eyes and look at the future that she is
starting to embody
there there are some things there one is
her capacity for discernment blows me
away so and i've heard that now um
you know this sort of the clarity the
seeing through the
um and nora was really moved by hearing
your
experience of having older kids now and
how they're not
met in the way that they were met and
this has started for my daughter ever
since she homeschooled um with us
until she was 14 but as soon as she went
over
to um public school she started
experiencing that a lot
that she was not being met the way she
was met at home
and with her peers in the homeschooling
community
and what what that is like to navigate
and how early grief can set in around
that and the kind of grief that i meet
in myself on a daily basis she was
meeting at age
you know 14 15. um but there's something
also that i see in her that i i gives me
a lot of hope and it's a
future where her sensitivity as in her
we raised her so that i feel like she
really didn't have to shut down much
like her
her open pores were able to stay very
open
and at the same time we've attempted and
you know it's an ongoing experiment like
she's still
growing up but we've attempted to build
us
within her with her a sturdiness from
the from the inside
so rather than shut down or protect the
sensitivity
actually to match that with an inner
sturdiness and i've seen
a resilience in her that also has
given me a lot of hope when i look at
the future in her eyes
because i i can see her already having
had
um some you know some some smaller but
some some small dark nights of her soul
and
how she has already been able within a
one
two year time frame being able to take
in the insights
learn the lessons and and literally
embody
the theory like she got it and now she
is
acting differently in relationships so
the
the quick turnaround um that also
gives gives me certainly a lot of hope
when i consider the future but
i don't want to end on this in difficult
note maybe but but it's real
and it's that i feel in the teenage
years right now and the teams that i'm
aware of
um that i'm meeting through her there
is a not taking for granted that there
is a future
and it's it it it i think it's huge
it's a great grief that is running
through them that they maybe have words
for and maybe not
but that is very different i think than
what i remember
when i was growing up i knew there were
big threats but i i felt assured of a
future
and so um yeah i just want to maybe add
in the context which i know we all hold
so closely to ourselves but
how much it really this is not just an
exercise that we need to bring theory
into embodiment this is like
sorry maybe you should use that
word this really really matters
okay i think i'm talking to everyone who
knows this but i'm just going to say it
so the universe hears it more
it really really matters that we
actually start
living in our cells in our bones in our
minds our hearts
our spirits our souls like we we bring
this
to life that that we feel the future is
calling for
because that might actually make a
future possible
well so i would like to take up this
topic on another high pitch
session i think this is this is really
uh this is
i don't even know what to say this is
really what's what's very important and
very
unsolved it's not it's not being taken
up and it's not solved
and i think the people that are here uh
are the people that are working on it i
mean no no for sure miriam this is
basically your life's work actually is
part of it now
um and for me it's very uh interesting
because
and i'll just kind of wrap up with this
non-personal but more of a conceptual
einstein predicted this he said the rate
of
change the rate of the change in
knowledge would be so
accelerated that from the perspective of
the children the parents would live in
the past
and then he said so then what is the
role of adults and educators
you're going to be faced with teaching
your child an
unknown and unknowable future
and for me as an educator one of the
things that
i teach one of the principles i take
from this is that if you look at
education today
we're constantly trying to teach
children the lessons that we learned
and this is completely irrelevant to
them
so first we have to put the problem in
and then show them how to solve it and
the problems they face
we haven't learned only they can learn
to solve them
so this transforms the relationship
between the adult and the child
and the teacher and the student and
that's something i
i would really like to
have one of these conversations around
with you
now i know we didn't get uh time for
question and answers
um this panel is a is you know it's a
pretty big panel and
i think the design is we wanted to show
many
uh different voices from within this
panel
one of the things that it's quite often
a complaint that there's not breakout
groups in time for participation
but what i want you to encourage you
is to create your own groups and
continue the conversation
in your own groups and hopefully this is
a uh this is a service that we can do is
to catalyze
continuing conversations off of these of
these conversations
so i want to thank peter for uh making
the space possible and encouraging me
and ah man i just so appreciative of
the women on this panel um
peter
um you want me to close uh
um okay uh
yeah i just and i don't mean this in a
sexual way but just listening i was very
turned on uh or maybe switched on as a
better
phrase and i just i just felt like my
body vibrating throughout that whole
session
um and i don't think the q a was missed
uh so i thought it was beautiful so
thank you benita and everyone for
for coming today uh we have another
session
penciled in not next week but the week
after so we'll circle back on email
see if that's the go and then we'll post
on the website
uh next event we have one in an hour
or 2 p.m eastern time with greg
henriquez and
zack stein's going to guest appear in
that one so if you want to check that
out you can rsp on the website
that being said i that's all i have to
say um so thanks so much
for coming to store
[Music]
so this is some good music that bonita
chose
thanks everybody thanks bonita thanks
peter
bye thank you for having